Chapter 87. The Grand Armada.
The long and narrow peninsula of Malaa extending southeastward from the
territories of Burma forms the most southerntherly point of all Asia. In a
continuous line from that peninsula stretch the long islands of Somatra,
Java, Bali and Teour which with many others form a vast mole or rampart
lengthwise connecting Asia with Australia and dividing the long unbroken
Indian Ocean from the thickly studded oriental archipelos.
This rampart is pierced by several sally ports for the convenience of ships and
whales conspicuous among which are these straits of Sunda and Malaca. By these
straits of Sunda chiefly vessels bound to China from the west emerge into the China seas.
Those narrow straits of Sunda divide Somatra from Java. And standing midway
in that vast rampart of islands, buttressed by that bold green promonary
known to Seaman as Java head, they not a little correspond to the central gateway
opening into some vast walled empire.
and considering the inexhaustible wealth of spices and silks and jewels and gold
and ivory with which the thousand islands of that oriental sea are
enriched. It seems a significant provision of nature that such treasures
by the very formation of the land should at least bear the appearance, however
ineffectual, of being guarded from the all grasping western world. The shores
of these straits of Sunda are unsupplied with those doineering fortresses which
guard the entrances to the Mediterranean, the Baltic and the propontis. Unlike the Danes, these
orientals do not demand the obsequious homage of lowered top sails from the
endless procession of ships before the wind, which for centuries past by night
and day, have passed between the islands of Sumatra and Java, freighted with the
costliest cargos of the east. But while they freely wave a ceremonial like this,
they do by no means renounce their claim to more solid tribute.
Time out of mind. The piratical proas of the melees, lurking among the lowshaded
coes and eyelets of Somatra have sied out upon the vessels sailing through the
straits, fiercely demanding tribute at the point of their spears. Though by the
repeated bloody chastisements they have received at the hands of European
cruisers, the audacity of these corsairs has of late been somewhat repressed. Yet
even at the present day we occasionally hear of English and American vessels
which in those waters have been remorselessly boarded and pillaged.
With a fair fresh wind the Peekquad was now drawing nigh to these straits. Ahab,
purposing to pass through them into the Javan seas, and then cruising northward
over waters known to be frequented here and there by the sperm whale, sweep
inshore by the Philippine Islands, and gain the far coast of Japan in time for
the great whailing season there. By these means, the circumnavigating
Peekquad would sweep almost all the known sperm whale cruising grounds of
the world, previous to descending upon the line in the Pacific, where Ahab,
though everywhere else foiled in his pursuit, firmly counted upon giving
battle to Moby Dick in the sea he was most known to frequent, and at a season
when he might most reasonably be presumed to be haunting it. But how now
in this zoned quest does Ahab touch no land? Does his crew drink air? Surely he
will stop for water. Nay, for a long time now the circus running son has
raced within his fiery ring and needs no sustenance but what's in himself. So
Ahab, mark this too in the whaler. While other hulls are loaded down with alien
stuff to be transferred to foreign warves, the world wandering whale ship
carries no cargo but herself and crew, their weapons, and their wants. She has
a whole lakes's contents bottled in her ample hold. She is ballasted with
utilities, not altogether with unusable pig lead and Kent ledge. She carries
years water in her clear old prime Nantucket water which when 3 years a
float the Nantucketer in the Pacific prefers to drink before the brackish
fluid but yesterday rafted off in casks from the Peruvian or Indian streams.
Hence it is that while other ships may have gone to China from New York and
back again touching at a score of ports, the whale ship in all that interval may
not have cited one grain of soil, her crew having seen no man but floating
seammen like themselves.
So that did you carry them the news that another flood had come, they would only
answer, "Well, boys, here's the ark."
Now, as many sperm whales had been captured off the western coast of Java
in the near vicinity of these straits of Sunda, indeed as most of the ground
roundabout was generally recognized by fishermen as an excellent spot for
cruising. Therefore, as the Peekquad gained more and more upon Java Head, the
lookouts were repeatedly hailed and admonished to keep wide awake. But
though the green palmy cliffs of the land soon loomed on the starboard bow,
and with delighted nostrils the fresh cinnamon was snuffed in the air, yet not
a single jet was described, almost renouncing all thoughts of falling in
with any game here, the ship had well nigh entered the straits, when the
customary cheering cry was heard from a loft, and heong a spectacle of singular
magnificence saluted us.
But here be it premise that owing to the unweied activity with which of late they
have been hunted over all four oceans, the sperm whales, instead of almost
invariably sailing in small detached companies as in former times, are now
frequently met with in extensive herds, sometimes embracing so great a multitude
that it would almost seem as if numerous nations of them had sworn solemn league
and covenant for mutual assistance and protection. To this aggregation of the
sperm whale into such immense caravans may be imputed the circumstance that
even in the best cruising grounds, you may now sometimes sail for weeks and
months together without being greeted by a single spout, and then suddenly be
saluted by what sometimes seems thousands on thousands.
broad on both boughs at a distance of some two or three miles and forming a
great semicircle embracing one half of the level horizon, a continuous chain of
whale jets were upplaying and sparkling in the noonday air. Unlike the straight
perpendicular twin jets of the right whale which dividing at top fall over in
two branches like the cleft drooping boughs of a willow, the single forward
slanting spout of the sperm whale presents a thick curled bush of white
mist continually rising and falling away to lured.
seen from the Peekquad's deck. Then, as she would rise on a high hill of the
sea, this host of vapory spouts, individually curling up into the air,
and beheld through a blending atmosphere of bluish haze, showed like the thousand
cheerful chimneys of some dense metropolis, described of a balmy,
autoutumnal morning by some horsemen on a height, as marching armies approaching an
unfriendly defile in the mountains accelerate their march, all eagerness to
place that perilous passage in their rear, and once more expand in
comparative security upon the plane.
Even so did this vast fleet of whales now seem hurrying forward through the
straits, gradually contracting the wings of their semicircle, and swimming on in
one solid but still crescentic center.
Crowding all sail, the Peekquad pressed after them, the harpooners handling
their weapons, and loudly cheering from the heads of their yet suspended boats.
If the wind only held, little doubt had they that chase through these straits of
Sunda, the vast host would only deploy into the oriental seas to witness the
capture of not a few of their number.
And who could tell whether in that congregated caravan Moby Dick himself
might not temporarily be swimming like the worshiped white elephant in the
coronation procession of the Siamese. So with Stunel piled on stun we sailed
along driving these Leviathans before us when of a sudden the voice of Tashego
was heard loudly directing attention to something in our wake.
Corresponding to the crescent in our van, we beheld another in our rear. It
seemed formed of detached white vapors rising and falling, something like the
spouts of the whales, only they did not so completely come and go, for they
constantly hovered without finally disappearing. Leveling his glass at this
site, Ahab quickly revolved in his pivot hole, crying, "Aloft there, and rig
whips and buckets to wet the sails.
Melees, sir, and after us.
As if too long lurking behind the headlands till the Peekquad should
fairly have entered the straits, these rascally Asiatics were now in hot
pursuit to make up for their overcautious delay. But when the swift
peekquad with a fresh leading wind was herself in hot chase, how very kind of
these tawny philanthropists to assist in speeding her onto her own chosen
pursuit, mere riding whips and rolls to her as they were. As with glass under
arm, Ahab and fro paced on the deck, in his forward turn, beholding the monsters
he chased, and in the after one the bloodthirsty pirates chasing him. some
such fancy as the above seemed his. And when he glanced upon the green walls of
the watery defile in which the ship was then sailing, and beth thought him that
through that gate lay the route to his vengeance, and beheld how through that
same gate he was now both chasing and being chased to his deadly end. And not
only that, but a herd of remorseless wild pirates and inhuman atheistical
devils were infernally cheering him on with their curses. When all these
conceits had passed through his brain, Ahab's brow was left gaunt and ribbed
like the black sand beach after some stormy tide has been gnawing it without
being able to drag the firm thing from its place.
But thoughts like these troubled very few of the reckless crew, and when,
after steadily dropping and dropping the pirates a stern, the Peekquad at last
shot by the vivid green cockatu point on the Sumatra side, emerging at last upon
the broad waters beyond. Then the harpooners seemed more to grieve that
the swift whales had been gaining upon the ship than to rejoice that the ship
had so victoriously gained upon the melees. But still driving on in the wake
of the whales, at length they seemed abading their speed. Gradually the ship
neared them, and the wind now dying away. Word was passed to spring to the
boats. But no sooner did the herd, by some presumed wonderful instinct of the
sperm whale, become notified of the three keels that were after them, though
as yet a mile in their rear, then they rallied again, and forming in close
ranks and battalions, so that their spouts all looked like flashing lines of
stacked bayonets moved on with redoubled velocity.
Stripped to our shirts and drawers, we sprang to the white ash, and after
several hours pulling, were almost disposed to renounce the chase, when a
general pausing commotion among the whales, gave animating token, that they
were now at last under the influence of that strange perplexity of inert
irresolution, which, when fishermen perceive it in the whale, they say he is
gallied. The compact marshall columns in which they had been hitherto rapidly and
steadily swimming were now broken up in one measurless route, and like King
Porus's elephant in the Indian battle with Alexander, they seemed going mad
with consternation. In all directions, expanding in vast, irregular circles,
and aimlessly swimming hither and thither by their short, thick spoutings,
they plainly betrayed their distraction of panic. This was still more strangely
evinced by those of their number who completely paralyzed as it were,
helplessly floated like waterlogged dismantled ships on the sea. Had these
Leviathans been but a flock of simple sheep pursued over the pasture by three
fierce wolves, they could not possibly have avinced such excessive dismay. But
this occasional timidity is characteristic of almost all hering
creatures. Though banding together in tens of thousands, the lion manaed
buffaloos of the west have fled before a solitary horsemen. Witness to all human
beings how when herded together in the sheepfold of a theat's pit, they will at
the slightest alarm of fire rush helter skelter for the outlets, crowding,
trampling, jamming, and remorselessly dashing each other to death. Best
therefore withhold any amazement at the strangely gallied whales before us. For
there is no folly of the beasts of the earth, which is not infinitely outdone
by the madness of men.
Though many of the whales, as has been said, were in violent motion, yet it is
to be observed that as a whole the herd neither advanced nor retreated, but
collectively remained in one place. As is customary in those cases, the boats
at once separated, each making for some one lone whale on the outskirts of the
shaw. In about 3 minutes time, Quiquig's harpoon was flung. The stricken fish
darted blinding spray in our faces, and then running away with us like light
steered straight for the heart of the herd. Though such a movement on the part
of the whale struck under such circumstances, is in no wise unprecedented, and indeed is almost
always more or less anticipated, yet does it present one of the more perilous
vicissitudes of the fishery. For as the swift monster drags you deeper and
deeper into the frantic shaw, you bid a due to circumspect life and only exist
in a delirious throbb. As blind and deaf, the whale plunged forward, as if
by sheer power of speed to rid himself of the iron leech that had fastened to
him, as we thus tore a white gash in the
sea, on all sides, menaced as we flew by the crazed creatures to and fro rushing
about us, our beset boat was like a ship mobbed by ice isles in a tempest, and
striving to steer through their complicated channels and straits, not
knowing at what moment it may be locked in and crushed.
But not a bit daunted, Quiquake steered us manfully, now shearing off from this
monster directly across our route in advance, now edging away from that whose
colossal flukes were suspended overhead, while all the time Starbucks stood up in
the boughs, lance in hand, pricking out of our way whatever whales he could
reach by short darts, for there was no time to make long ones. Nor were the
oresmen quite idle, though their wanted duty was now altogether dispensed with.
They chiefly attended to the shouting part of the business. "Out of the way,
Commodore!" cried one, to a great dramadary that of a sudden rose bodily
to the surface, and for an instant threatened to swamp us. "Hard down with
your tail there," cried a second to another, which close to our gunnel,
seemed calmly cooling himself with his own fan-like extremity.
All whaleboats carry certain curious contrivances originally invented by the
Nantucket Indians called drugs. Two thick squares of wood of equal size are
stoutly clenched together so that they cross each other's grain at right
angles. A line of considerable length is then attached to the middle of this
block and the other end of the line being looped. It can in a moment be
fastened to a harpoon. It is chiefly among giided whales that this drug is
used, for then more whales are close around you than you can possibly chase
at one time. But sperm whales are not everyday encountered, while you may,
then you must kill all you can. And if you cannot kill them all at once, you
must wing them so that they can be afterwards killed at your leisure. Hence
it is that at times like these the drug comes into requisition. Our boat was
furnished with three of them. The first and second were successfully darted, and
we saw the whales staggeringly running off, fettered by the enormous sidelong
resistance of the towing drug. They were cramped like malifactors with the chain
and ball, but upon flinging the third, in the act of tossing overboard the
clumsy wooden block, it caught under one of the seats of the boat, and in an
instant tore it out and carried it away, dropping the orarsmen in the boat's
bottom, as the seat slid from under him.
On both sides the sea came in at the wounded planks, but we stuffed two or
three drawers and shirts in, and so stopped the leaks for the time.
It had been next to impossible to dart these drugged harpoons, were it not that
as we advanced into the herd, our whales way greatly diminished, moreover, that
as we went still further and further from the circumference of commotion, the
dire disorders seemed waning, so that when at last the jerking harpoon drew
out, and the towing whale sideways vanished, then with the tapering force
of his parting momentum, we glided between two whales into the innermost
heart of the shaw. As if from some mountain torrent we had slid into a
serene valley lake. Here the storms in the roaring glenns between the outermost
whales were heard but not felt. In this central expanse the sea presented that
smooth satin-like surface called a sleek produced by the subtle moisture thrown
off by the whale in his more quiet moods. Yes, we were now in that
enchanted calm which they say lurks at the heart of every commotion. And still
in the distracted distance, we beheld the tumults of the outer concentric
circles, and saw successive pods of whales, eight or 10 in each, swiftly
going round and round, like multiplied spans of horses in a ring, and so
closely shoulderto-shoulder, that a titanic circus rider might easily have
overarched the middle ones, and so have gone round on their backs, owing to the
density of the crowd of reposing whales more immediately surrounding ing the
embedded axis of the herd. No possible chance of escape was at present afforded
us. We must watch for a breach in the living wall that hemmed us in, the wall
that had only admitted us in order to shut us up. Keeping at the center of the
lake, we were occasionally visited by small, tame cows and calves, the women
and children of this routed host.
Now, inclusive of the occasional wide intervals between the revolving outer
circles, and inclusive of the spaces between the various pods in any one of
those circles, the entire area at this juncture, embraced by the whole
multitude, must have contained at least two or three square miles. At any rate,
though indeed such a test at such a time might be deceptive, spoutings might be
discovered from our low boat that seemed playing up almost from the rim of the
horizon. I mention this circumstance because, as if the cows and calves had
been purposely locked up in this innermost fold, and as if the wide
extent of the herd, had hitherto prevented them from learning the precise
cause of its stopping, or possibly being so young, unsophisticated, in every way
innocent, and inexperienced, however it may have been, these smaller whales, now
and then visiting our bealed boat from the margin of the lake, evinced a
wondrous fearlessness and confidence, or else a still be charmed panic, which it
was impossible not to marvel at. Like household dogs, they came snuffling
round us right up to our gunnels and touching them, till it almost seemed
that some spell had suddenly domesticated them. Quiquake patted their
foreheads. Starbucks scratched their backs with his lance, but fearful of the
consequences, for the time, refrained from darting it.
But far beneath this wondrous world upon the surface, another and still stranger
world met our eye as we gazed over the side. For suspended in those watery
vaults floated the forms of the nursing mothers of the whales, and those that of
their enormous girth seemed shortly to become mothers. The lake, as I have
hinted, was to a considerable depth exceedingly transparent, and as human
infants, while suckling, will calmly and fixly gaze away from the breast, as if
leading two different lives at the time, and while yet drawing mortal
nourishment, be still spiritually feasting upon some unearly reminiscence.
Even so did the young of these whales seem looking up towards us but not at us
as if we were but a bit of gulf weede in their newborn sight. Floating on their
sides the mothers also seemed quietly eyeing us. One of these little infants
that from certain queer tokens seemed hardly a day old might have measured
some 14 ft in length and some 6 ft in girth. He was a little frisky, though as
yet his body seemed scarce yet recovered from that irksome position it had so
lately occupied in the maternal reticule, where tail to head and all
ready for the final spring, the unborn whale lies bent like a tartar's bow. The
delicate side fins and the palms of his flukes still freshly retained the
pleated, crumbled appearance of a baby's ears newly arrived from foreign parts.
Line, line, cried quick, looking over the gunnel. Him fast him fast. Who line
him? Who struck? Do whale? One big, one little. What a ye man? Cried Starbucks.
Lookie here, said Quiquake, pointing down.
as when the stricken whale that from the tub is reeled out hundreds of fathoms of
rope, as after deep sounding he floats up again, and shows the slackened
curling line buoyantly rising and spiraling towards the air, so now
Starbucks saw long coils of the umbilical cord of Madame Leviathan, by
which the young cub seems still tethered to its dam, not seldom in the rapid
vicissitudes of the chase, this natural line, with the maternal end loose
becomes entangled with the hempen one so that the cub is thereby trapped. Some of
the subtlest secrets of the sea seem to vulge to us in this enchanted pond. We
saw young Leviathan amors in the deep.
Footnote. The sperm whale, as with all other species of the Leviathan, but
unlike most other fish, breeds indifferently at all seasons, after a
gestation which may probably be set down at 9 months, producing but one at a
time, though in some few known instances, giving birth to an Esau and a
Jacob, a contingency provided for in suckling by two teeth, curiously
situated, one on each side of the anus, but the breasts themselves extend
upwards from hat. When by chance these precious parts in a nursing whale are
cut by the hunter's lance, the mother's pouring milk and blood rivalingly
discolor the sea for rods. The milk is very sweet and rich. It has been tasted
by man. It might do well with strawberries. When overflowing with
mutual esteem, the whales salute morum.
End of footnote.
And thus, though surrounded by circle upon circle of consternations and a
frights, did these inscrable creatures at the center freely and fearlessly
indulge in all peaceful concernments, yay, serenely reveled in diance and
delight. But even so, amid the tornadoed Atlantic of my being, do I myself still
forever centrally disport in mute calm, and while ponderous planets of unwaning
woe revolve around me, deep down and deep inland, there I still bathe me in
eternal mildness of joy.
Meanwhile, as we thus lay entranced, the occasional sudden frantic spectacles in
the distance against the activity of the other boats, still engaged in drugging
the whales on the frontier of the host, or possibly carrying on the war within
the first circle, where abundance of room and some convenient retreats were
afforded them. But the sight of the enraged, drugged whales, now and then
blindly darting to and fro across the circles, was nothing to what at last met
our eyes. It is sometimes the custom, when fast to a whale more than commonly
powerful and alert, to seek to hamstring him, as it were, by sundering or maming
his gigantic tail tendon. It is done by darting a short-handled cutting spade to
which is attached a rope for hauling it back again. A whale, wounded, as we
afterwards learned, in this part, but not effectually, as it seemed, had
broken away from the boat, carrying along with him half of the harpoon line,
and in the extraordinary agony of the wound, he was now dashing among the
revolving circles like the lone mounted desperado Arnold at the Battle of
Saratoga, carrying dismay wherever he went.
But agonizing as was the wound of this whale, and an appalling spectacle enough
anyway, yet the peculiar horror with which he seemed to inspire the rest of
the herd, was owing to a cause which at first the intervening distance obscured
from us. But at length we perceive that by one of the unimaginable accidents of
the fishery, this whale had become entangled in the harpoon line that he
towed. He had also run away with the cutting spade in him, and while the free
end of the rope attached to that weapon had permanently caught in the coils of
the harpoon line round his tail, the cutting spade itself had worked loose
from his flesh, so that tormented to madness, he was now churning through the
water, violently flaying with his flexible tail, and tossing the keen
spade about him, wounding and murdering his own comrades.
This terrific object seemed to recall the whole herd from their stationary
fright. First the whales forming the margin of our lake began to crowd a
little and tumble against each other as if lifted by half spent billows from
afar. Then the lake itself began faintly to heave and swell. The submarine bridal
chambers and nurseries vanished. In more and more contracting orbits, the whales
in the more central circles began to swim in thickening clusters. Yes, the
long calm was departing. A low advancing hum was soon heard, and then, like the
tumultuous masses of block ice, when the great river Hudson breaks up in the
spring, the entire host of whales came tumbling upon their inner center, as if
to pile themselves up in one common mountain. Instantly, Starbucks and
Quiquake changed places. Starbucks taking the stern. Oars, oars, he
intensely whispered, ceasing the helm.
Grip your oars and clutch your souls now. My god, men, stand by. Shove him
off, you quiquake the whale there. Prick him. Hit him. Stand up. Stand up and
stay. So, spring men, pull men, never mind their backs. Scrape them. scrape away.
The boat was now all but jammed between two vast black bulks, leaving a narrow
dinels between their long lengths. But by desperate endeavor, we at last shot
into a temporary opening, then giving way rapidly, and at the same time
earnestly watching for another outlet.
After many similar hair breath escapes, we at last swiftly glided into what had
just been one of the outer circles, but now crossed by random whales, all
violently making for one center. This lucky salvation was cheaply purchased by
the loss of Quequ's hat, who, while standing in the boughs to prick the
fugitive whales, had his hat taken clean from his head by the air eddy made by
the sudden tossing of a pair of broad flukes close by.
Riotous and disordered as the universal commotion now was, it soon resolved
itself into what seemed a systematic movement, for having clumped together at
last in one dense body, they then renewed their onward flight with
augmented fleetness. Further pursuit was useless, but the boat still lingered in
their wake to pick up what drugged whales might be dropped a stern, and
likewise to secure one which Flask had killed and wafted. The waif is a penant
pole, two or three of which are carried by every boat, and which when additional
game is at hand, are inserted upright into the floating body of a dead whale,
both to mark its place on the sea, and also as token of prior possession should
the boats of any other ship draw near.
The result of this lowering was somewhat illustrative of that sagacious saying in
the fishery, the more whales, the less fish. Of all the drugged whales, only
one was captured. The rest contrived to escape for the time, but only to be
taken, as will hereafter be seen, by some other craft than the Peekquad.